[SPEAKER_01]: I was taught meditation in a...
[SPEAKER_01]: I could sort of describe how... what I was taught.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it involved being aware of sensations in the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: We talked about the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: We talked about focusing in the previous talk.
[SPEAKER_01]: But what's meant by that?
[SPEAKER_01]: Sensations of the body is meant... it's basically... you're supposed to focus on what's purely physical.
[SPEAKER_01]: The physical sensations.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's purely... no mental, no imagination, no visualizing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just the pure mental.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're supposed to access the pure physical pressure, throbbing, tingling.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whatever it is.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's the first aspect to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, the idea is to not react to that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, to not mentally react to that.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the idea was that what the Buddha means...
[SPEAKER_01]: Isn't that all your reaction?
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, so... Where do you start?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, so, this, the idea was that this was what saṅkhara is, what the Buddha meant by the word saṅkhara.
[SPEAKER_01]: Saṅkhara is this
[SPEAKER_01]: Mental reactions to the physical sensations or physical... what's going on physically.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: And so, the idea is that you don't react to those physical sensations.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if you don't react, then you're not creating saṅkharas.
[SPEAKER_01]: And when you're not creating new saṅkharas,
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, reactions.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, old saṅkharas come to the surface as physical sensations that, again, you don't react to.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if you keep not reacting to this, these, this, then you're removing or getting rid of or purifying
[SPEAKER_01]: An old stock of old reactions, old saṅkharas.
[SPEAKER_01]: How would you know that?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because in the future, if you do it for long enough, you'll become enlightened, because you'll get rid of all of your past stock of saṅkharas.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can't know that now, but in the future, if you keep doing this, at some point in the future... You just have to take it in trust.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: And not be able to verify it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes, that's right.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because your only way of relating
[SPEAKER_02]: Your only conceivable relationship with saṅkharas is to have body sensations.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's right.
[SPEAKER_02]: Which means the presently manifested body sensations that then you ascribe to be previous saṅkharas.
[SPEAKER_02]: Pool of previous saṅkharas is basically somewhere in my unconscious.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's somewhere hidden.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's right.
[SPEAKER_02]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: Or it's... or you're not perceiving it.
[SPEAKER_02]: I think you...
[SPEAKER_02]: I think the idea...
[SPEAKER_02]: So, how can you have a thread that you can know, that you can discern, that you can reflect upon, between something that's from unconscious and something you're conscious, that you can say, I see the connection between the two, because you will be conscious of that, which means it's not unconscious.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you can only take it on trust and never ever be able to verify that there are these accumulated saṅkharas that mysteriously manifest as bodily sensations.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, it provides a story.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, that's basically one of the...
[SPEAKER_02]: It provides a nice psychological explanation.
[SPEAKER_02]: Look, I see all these things coming or going.
[SPEAKER_02]: It doesn't really require any kind of, you know, existential type of effort that will result in anxiety or doubt.
[SPEAKER_02]: I just need to monitor these random sensations and, in my mind, develop, like, a fanciful, pleasing
[SPEAKER_01]: Right, right, right.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have to start by taking things in
[SPEAKER_02]: But this, you can't verify.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: How can you become conscious of the unconscious?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Saṅkharas, before they're manifested, and then know them as being there, waiting to show themselves on the surface of your body.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's just assumption on top of assumption on top of assumption, that you cannot even verify.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're just acting out of it, because it pleases you.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's one problem, rather quite fundamental problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: And also, also, how can you, how can you experience pure physicality?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, that was the first point, you know.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's like, you attempt to something purely physical.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_02]: If you're attending to it.
[SPEAKER_02]: You have no thought of it in your mind.
[SPEAKER_02]: If it's purely physical, means you are not thinking it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yet, how are you talking about it?
[SPEAKER_02]: How is it manifest?
[SPEAKER_02]: How are you knowing it?
[SPEAKER_02]: How can you attend it?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Attention is not physical.
[SPEAKER_02]: Your mind acts upon that which is completely
[SPEAKER_02]: That is the object of the faculty of the mind.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yet, here you are, practicing Buddhism, practicing dhamma, rooted in a belief that you can perceive, non-mentally, matter.
[SPEAKER_02]: That is the pure matter.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's a pure experience of the matter.
[SPEAKER_02]: There is no thought or mind involved in it whatsoever.
[SPEAKER_02]: How is that even conceivable?
[SPEAKER_02]: Except as a thought.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's one problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: The other problem, obviously, is how can you choose to not react?
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, yeah, there was a second point.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Also, there are these things happening in my body, these sensations.
[SPEAKER_02]: And I am choosing to not react upon that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Which is your current reaction.
[SPEAKER_02]: Exactly, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: It might be a better reaction than reacting immediately impulsively.
[SPEAKER_02]: Restraining yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's still a reaction, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you developing a belief that you're restraining a particular type of reaction on account of the action of restraint, that's not reaction.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, that's a wrong view because it contradicts itself.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, yeah, you should restrain yourself if that's what you're doing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: But if you're restraining yourself and holding a view that restraining yourself is not the action, it's not the choice, it's completely beyond it, means you'll not look for that which really is beyond it.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why sense-restraint itself cannot result in enlightenment.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's a good thing to do, but it cannot enlighten you because, as you can see, you can still hold and develop even further wrong views on account of it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, it's like, oh, stop thinking, stop thinking.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's a thought that you have in your mind, that claims to have stopped thinking, or that can stop thinking, by thinking.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why wrong views are wrong, because they will, at some point, at some level, contain some contradiction.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, also, you can say, I mean, I don't see how
[SPEAKER_01]: Any of this that I've been describing can help somebody to discern the nature of the aggregates.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, I mean, like, so, basically, you've got... you're saying that you... you attend to pure matter by feeling it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And by not perceiving it with your mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, when you're talking of describing the feeling, you're talking about pressure and throbbing and tingling.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, they're all perceptions.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, perception, feeling,
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, saṅkhara manifests itself as matter, but this is your past intentions.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, your past intentions manifest as material which you feel.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's all... basically, it's all... everything's all mushed together.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can't... how is... how is continuing to do that going to help you to make sense of it?
[SPEAKER_02]: And also, if you're not able to verify the whole thing of my past saṅkharas right now, how could have then the first person
[SPEAKER_02]: You couldn't have known that.
[SPEAKER_02]: I would say...
[SPEAKER_02]: If you said you can only know it once you become enlightened, how did the first person become enlightened?
[SPEAKER_02]: He couldn't have taken that on trust, because there was nobody to tell him.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, how did the Buddha became the Buddha then?
[SPEAKER_02]: By verifying things that you can verify for yourself, and then instructing others to do the same.
[SPEAKER_02]: And if I tell you, well, this is your past thing, this is your unconscious thing, means it's non-existent.
[SPEAKER_02]: We can't talk about it.
[SPEAKER_01]: We can't.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you talking about it means it's not unconscious anymore.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can talk about it, but once you do, it ceases to be that which is in the unconscious, because you are consciously designating it.
[SPEAKER_02]: How's that possible?
[SPEAKER_02]: Same when the people say, oh, the God, the ultimate reality, you can't express in words.
[SPEAKER_02]: You just expressed it.
[SPEAKER_02]: That is its expression.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, you can't put it in words.
[SPEAKER_01]: You just put it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That ineffable thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: You only wish things would be that easy, in terms of enlightenment.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I guess the question arises, then, if saṅkharas aren't this past stock of your previous reactions, the manifests on your body, physically, that you should feel, or perceive, or whatever.
[SPEAKER_01]: Until it all gets weared away and all the stuff.
[SPEAKER_01]: If that's the wrong way of thinking about saṅkhara, then the question arises, what did the Buddha mean when he talks about saṅkhara?
[SPEAKER_01]: I think that's a... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, it's, you know, it's something that most people, even the teachers,
[SPEAKER_02]: We don't necessarily dwell on it sufficiently enough.
[SPEAKER_02]: It will provide you an explanation for it, or use it to describe anything basically ambiguous that you have.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, energies, theories, thinkings, patterns.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, saṅkhara, saṅkharas.
[SPEAKER_02]: This is mystical entities, basically, which you need to overcome.
[SPEAKER_02]: But literally, the Pali word saṅkhara means what?
[SPEAKER_02]: Binding together, keeping
[SPEAKER_02]: It's basically something responsible for things to be things, in a way.
[SPEAKER_02]: But not... That's the thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: No pun intended.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not in a sense that...
[SPEAKER_02]: It's some sort of explanation of a universal structure of your experience.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's something that pertains to the sense of self.
[SPEAKER_02]: And, as the Buddha said, extinguishing of saṅkhara pertains to liberation of the atavāda and everything else.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, because, you know, there will be a tendency to think of saṅkharas in the way that Jñānavīra was thinking about it, which is theoretically true, but practically not necessarily adequate.
[SPEAKER_02]: You want to see them from the point of view of the self-view, from the point of view of appropriation.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because once you do that, saṅkharas are gone.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay?
[SPEAKER_02]: So, what is then?
[SPEAKER_02]: For somebody who is a sense of self, which means that inevitably has to be rooted in a sense of ownership of things, and now you have somebody who isn't anymore his own, who has relinquished his sense of ownership.
[SPEAKER_02]: What's the difference?
[SPEAKER_02]: It's obviously not in things that are there.
[SPEAKER_02]: They were taken as mine and now not taken as mine.
[SPEAKER_02]: Those things remain the same.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, what's the difference
[SPEAKER_02]: Absence of saṅkhara means absence of taking things as mine.
[SPEAKER_02]: And it is that very act of taking things as mine that forms your sense of self.
[SPEAKER_02]: Hence formations, or determines your sense of self, hence determinations, or the makers, the I-making, the my-making, and what not, what a big Buddhist translation was.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: The point is, without taking things as mine, you cannot be determining, forming, maintaining the formation of your sense of self.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you stop taking things as mine, you stop fueling the sense.
[SPEAKER_02]: It will have to fade.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's what Buddha said about a king.
[SPEAKER_02]: The king wouldn't be a king without his king's possessions, king's ownerships that make him a king.
[SPEAKER_02]: He's not a king.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, if you yourself maintain things that make you yourself, that's why you are responsible for your own self-view.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's what saṅkharas are.
[SPEAKER_02]: If you look at them in your body, your sensations, none of that is owned already.
[SPEAKER_02]: You're already dismissing it.
[SPEAKER_02]: You want to look where, where, where is sense of self?
[SPEAKER_02]: Where, where, where is my own sense of self?
[SPEAKER_02]: Where is my own sense of ownership?
[SPEAKER_02]: Where are the things that are dear to me?
[SPEAKER_02]: Where are the things that, sort of, I find pleasing?
[SPEAKER_02]: I would be emotionally disturbed if I were to lose.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's where you look for saṅkharas.
[SPEAKER_02]: Maybe like my, my meditation technique.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, yeah, once you've had some time, yeah, they can become
[SPEAKER_02]: Again, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Basically, whenever there is a basis for suffering, means there is the appropriation, there are saṅkharas.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: There are determinations that determine you as a sense of self.
[SPEAKER_01]: But can you not...
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, maybe this is more what Hanavira is saying.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can talk about saṅkharas in a more general sense.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can talk about a particular type of saṅkharas.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: But why are we talking about it in the first place?
[SPEAKER_02]: Because we all want to be free.
[SPEAKER_02]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: We want to be arahants.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you don't talk about them in any other sense.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_02]: Unless you're free.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why, that's why I mean, like, it's not incorrect to say that saṅkhara is a determination of the five aggregates, as Avinābhira did.
[SPEAKER_02]: But it's inaccurate practically, because now somebody will read that and think, oh, I understood what saṅkharas are, while he's still a putujana.
[SPEAKER_01]: But wouldn't it be helpful for a lot of people to think that determinations, or saṅkhara, or whatever you want to call it...
[SPEAKER_02]: If they have absolutely no other reference point in regard to saṅkharas...
[SPEAKER_01]: It's more to do with what things mean.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not to do with things
[SPEAKER_01]: No, of course, of course.
[SPEAKER_02]: What I'm saying now is that if you have no other reference as to what saṅkharas are, one in the way I described, it's better.
[SPEAKER_02]: But now that you can have even more accurate reference, the one I'm showing you, this is redundant.
[SPEAKER_02]: I see, okay.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's not it's not helpful then.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that's the whole point.
[SPEAKER_02]: Where are the things that I own?
[SPEAKER_02]: Why do I own them?
[SPEAKER_02]: Because you don't realize you can't own them.
[SPEAKER_02]: Hence, ignorance determines the sense of ownership.
[SPEAKER_02]: Ignorance determines... Yeah, avijjā, pācchā, sankhāra.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's the most practical thing you can have.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's nothing abstract.
[SPEAKER_02]: Unless, of course, you have no idea what it is, in case...
[SPEAKER_02]: It's everything abstract.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_02]: And it's certainly not
[SPEAKER_02]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: What difference does it make?
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you can observe all you want and try to manage and sort of tailor your responses and your behavior to whatever's happening.
[SPEAKER_02]: Fundamentally, you're fully appropriating the body as a whole.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you can dismiss the legs, you can dismiss everything, but overall, it's still my body.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, really...
[SPEAKER_02]: So, I'm only trying to avoid the part by ignoring the whole.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Deal with the part by ignoring the ownership of the whole.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, to find what saṅkharas are...
[SPEAKER_02]: You begin by looking for something which is dear to you, something that you care about, something which is... You have to start on the emotional basis, and then see what that emotional basis depends upon, and then look at the characteristics of that.
[SPEAKER_02]: As we described anicca as unownable.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's what saṅkharas are.
[SPEAKER_02]: Hence, you understand what saṅkharas are.
[SPEAKER_02]: You're not ignorant of them.
[SPEAKER_02]: There are no saṅkharas that determine you as you anymore.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because it requires you to not know that, to maintain that.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, yeah, by all means, abandon all saṅkharas.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not through your, like, mechanical management, quasi-psychological sort of meditation technique, but by understanding what they are.
[SPEAKER_02]: And you'll understand them.
[SPEAKER_02]: You will understand what they are, if you look where they are.
[SPEAKER_02]: And they are where your sense of ownership is.
[SPEAKER_02]: Determinations, formations, all that.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's always... it's always a background phenomenon.
[SPEAKER_01]: Of course, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, people going, oh, this... these saṅkhara's in my knees.
[SPEAKER_01]: In my knees, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Would that knee be your knee, if you already distinguish the ownership of the entire body as a whole?
[SPEAKER_02]: If you fully understood that what this body is, like, liable to, what these elements will go back to, that they can't be yours to begin with, this body cannot be yours even if you want it to,
[SPEAKER_02]: The only way to maintain it yours is to ignore the fact that it can't be yours.
[SPEAKER_02]: And people ignore that fact when they refuse to think about death, they refuse to think about sickness, aging, losing the loved ones and so on.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's how you ignore it.
[SPEAKER_02]: And you ignore it because it's unpleasant to think about it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, when you start with a sense of ownership, thinking about how you cannot own things that are dear to you is very unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's why people don't do it.
[SPEAKER_02]: As simple as that.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, would you then, if you don't, if you do start reflecting like that, and you genuinely develop complete dispassion towards your own body and what happens to it, would you still be concerned about a random tingling sensation in my knee?
[SPEAKER_02]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because I already abandoned the whole domain.
[SPEAKER_02]: What difference does it make?
[SPEAKER_02]: And then you wouldn't also be concerned from, like, agreeable things that happen to your body.
[SPEAKER_02]: Agreeable food, agreeable sounds.
[SPEAKER_02]: Disagreeable sounds wouldn't bother you either, because you have abandoned the whole domain of the body.
[SPEAKER_02]: And you won't abandon the domain of the body, the nature of the body, by staring at its particular parts.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because you're losing, because of the force, the determination, the act of staring at this, you are then willingly excluding the whole picture.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't do it both.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you can only discern what is meant by body, when the Buddha talks about body, by looking at experience as a whole, by
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's when people think, oh, well, no, you develop the focusing first, and then you look.
[SPEAKER_02]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because when you look back, you will look in the same manner in front of me.
[SPEAKER_02]: Overly attending, focusing on it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Which means, what you're gonna see, it's not gonna be the background of your attention.
[SPEAKER_02]: The only thing you know to do is attend, attend, focus, focus, focus.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay, now I focus on that which is behind my focusing.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, now that's your focus, and something else is behind, and you have no means of discerning it, because all you know is how to stare at what you focused on.
[SPEAKER_01]: And so, really, seeing saṅkharas means learning how to allow the background to be... You know, yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: To allow that to manifest in a way that manifests.
[SPEAKER_02]: But in a more direct sense, it's allowing, like, even your sense of ownership to manifest.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So that you can see its basis as unownable.
[SPEAKER_02]: If you see the impermanence of saṅkharas, as in
[SPEAKER_02]: I'm not in charge of this.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'm not in control.
[SPEAKER_02]: You cannot maintain atavāda any further then.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that's the point here.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because if you think you sort of, ah, there is no self, I already dealt with that simply by denying it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Now, I just need to look at these mysterious manifestations from my unconscious pool of consciousness through these saṅkharas and somehow, you know,
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, your starting point there is to stop denying all that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: And to recognize that there are still things that are dear to you, that you're not addressing.
[SPEAKER_02]: You're hoping that by doing such and such technique, you will magically address all the things that you are still liable to.
[SPEAKER_02]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: The only way to address things you're liable to is to go face to face with things you are liable to.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's right, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: There is no skillful means or any kind of
[SPEAKER_02]: sort of a carry over.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'll do this and it will magically free me from that.
[SPEAKER_02]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: The only way to free yourself from things you're subjected to, things you're burdened by, is to start unravelling the burden.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, which you can only do if you acknowledge the burden.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: There is I am.
[SPEAKER_02]: There is sense of ownership.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Start there.
[SPEAKER_02]: Now, within that, I need to find, basically, I need to learn how to
[SPEAKER_02]: And so, that can only be found through the things, like, not... That are yours.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's, it's... That's, that's another idea.
[SPEAKER_02]: When people think, like, oh, ownership is a problem, so I'll throw away my
[SPEAKER_02]: You don't need to own things already to be a subject to ownership, because you already own your body, your senses.
[SPEAKER_02]: You own your senses, you own anything that can come through your senses.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, if you think that throwing away things will free you from ownership, means you're making yourself even more deluded in regard to the nature of ownership, which is on the level of the senses, on the level of the body, on the level of the sankhāras.
[SPEAKER_02]: But if you remove the ownership from that level through fully understanding how unownable those things are, and by that I mean impermanent, by that I mean anicca,
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, as the Buddha said, he himself can stay in the king's palaces, eat two bowlfuls of food and whatnot, and not own anything, not be attached to anything, because he abandoned the whole domain where these things can manifest.
[SPEAKER_02]: He's free from sankhāras.
[SPEAKER_02]: Ownership is at that level, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not the... like you said before, it's not the things.
[SPEAKER_02]: Exactly, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, understanding itself is determined.
[SPEAKER_00]: Self-determination.
[SPEAKER_02]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, it's determined by your effort to understand.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's what the Buddha said when they asked him, is nibbāna determined?
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, it's undetermined as a phenomenon, but in a way, it's determined.
[SPEAKER_02]: And he said, nibbāna is determined by the practice of a holy life.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, your understanding, if you reach it, is determined by
[SPEAKER_02]: So, in that sense, it's determined.
[SPEAKER_02]: But those determinations cannot be owned.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you were saying that self is determined by...
[SPEAKER_01]: Seeing that self is determined.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Self is determined.
[SPEAKER_02]: I thought you said understanding self.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, to understand that self is determined... That's determined.
[SPEAKER_00]: That is understanding saṅkhara, that saṅkhara that you're supposed to understand.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, sure.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_02]: Saṅkharas are to be only understood correctly, first, if you accept your sense of self and the ownership, things that are dear to you.
[SPEAKER_02]: Saṅkharas are not understood in a sense of, look, this tree is impermanent, anicca, unownable.
[SPEAKER_02]: All these saṅkharas will come to pass.
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't care about that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not concerning yourself.
[SPEAKER_02]: But I'm saying that even that understanding, in a way, it's also determined by your efforts to understand.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that experience, it cannot be taken as mine.
[SPEAKER_02]: It cannot be appropriated.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why it's said nibbāna is asankhata.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not determined by the determination of ownership.
[SPEAKER_02]: But it is determined by your previous efforts to develop it and practice it.
[SPEAKER_02]: But now that's done.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why it's irreversible.
[SPEAKER_00]: But as... as someone starting out, when you read all saṅkharas of Nietzsche, means anything... self... that's what I'm saying, all self-determinations.
[SPEAKER_01]: Everything that determines your sense of self.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, yes, yes.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, the plurality of saṅkharas, it's through the singularity of the sense of self.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's how you can only see it rightly.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not like, that's impermanent, that's impermanent, that's impermanent, that's impermanent.
[SPEAKER_02]: Thus,
[SPEAKER_02]: I am not my own.
[SPEAKER_02]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: I am myself.
[SPEAKER_02]: Then, I read about that I can't be my own, because I'm not my own master, as in, I am not in control of my own life, my senses, etc.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, within that sense of I am, you then find all these other things that could be determining you, that are determining you, and then you realize they are unownable.
[SPEAKER_02]: And the reason they are unownable is because they're plural.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, the singular mastery, the sense of self-mastery, is always singular.
[SPEAKER_00]: As I was saying, self-determination.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: It undermines that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Self-determination.
[SPEAKER_02]: No, that's an important point, because people would, even this, where we're speaking, would probably, could understand as, okay, so you just find these random things, and then, sort of, reflect how they cannot be yours.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's accurate in theory, but in practice, you want to do that through your sense of self, not left, right, up or down, before or after.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, what is determining this thing?
[SPEAKER_02]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, first, you have to kind of start in the reverse order, the right order.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, I am, I am such-and-such, I am such-and-such in such-and-such situation.
[SPEAKER_02]: Now, there is obviously some emotional engagement, because there has to be something felt.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's the basis through which you start looking at things that are dear to you.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why, like, mindfulness of death, done rightly, will uproot anything, everything, because it pertains to the absolute fundamental appropriation of your experience as a whole, of the body, senses, all of that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's always a kind of... Those things will be seen as determinations...
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: ...only through the sense of self.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's exactly what determination is.
[SPEAKER_02]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's like negative.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's why people get confused.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why the Buddha himself said, when he described various aggregates, he said, this is what matter is, this is what feeling is, this is what perception is, but determination is in consciousness.
[SPEAKER_02]: Then, what is matter?
[SPEAKER_02]: This is matter.
[SPEAKER_02]: What is determination?
[SPEAKER_02]: And then list the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, yes, everything can be a determination if your sense of self depends on it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Which means, in order to see it as a determination, you need to see it through your sense of self.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not like, oh, yes, look, out there, that's impermanent.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's seeing the context where you're at.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the context is self.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: It is.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is the context where I start from.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's myself.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, even if you look at the same thing,
[SPEAKER_02]: But if you don't look at it through the sense of self, through the right context, you're not seeing it as a determination.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because it isn't determining a sense of self.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because determination is more of a relationship between your sense of self and things that make your sense of self.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that pertains to... to the sense of self, because that's the sole problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: Seeing that context of self is determined by the content that I'm taking as pertaining to me, mine.
[SPEAKER_00]: That seeing that undermines the ignorance of that situation.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's seen in that order.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because sense of self depends upon certain
[SPEAKER_02]: So, now you go and look at the individual, the crown, the cape, the throne, all these things.
[SPEAKER_02]: But now, they are the things that are determination for him.
[SPEAKER_02]: And even if you are king yourself, they are determining you.
[SPEAKER_02]: But the only way to see them as determination is first to see them through your kinghood, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_02]: Through your sense of self, what you are, and then see how this sense of self that's present and enduring, simultaneously, is now, in the right order, determined by these things at the same time.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's not determined by you choosing to be king.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's determined by you choosing to own these things that, oh, can be taken away.
[SPEAKER_02]: Thus, your sense of, I'm a king, can also
[SPEAKER_02]: And if you forget that, it would be like, okay, I'm a king.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, and now you start examining your crown.
[SPEAKER_02]: You do... oh, this crown is impermanent.
[SPEAKER_01]: Focus on it.
[SPEAKER_01]: This is impermanent.
[SPEAKER_01]: Focus, focus, focus, focus.
[SPEAKER_02]: Look at what it's made of to prove that the whole is impermanent.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then all these things... And never ever, for a single second, do things in the right order whereby first you start, I am a king.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's determined by this.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not, I am a king that has all of this.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because that's like, I am, this is mine.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's other way around.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because there are things that are mine, through that sense of I am.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, you don't start with, I'm a king, and now I get my... And now I go to the next subject.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm a king.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why I keep insisting...
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm first, and everything else second.
[SPEAKER_01]: Although, actually, probably, that's probably what the patujana would assume.
[SPEAKER_01]: They would think that.
[SPEAKER_01]: They would think, first of all, this is who I am, and then, that's why I'm given these things.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why they will still be a patujana, for as long as they don't approve that view.
[SPEAKER_02]: Realizing that... And that's why whenever we do a contemplation, whenever we do
[SPEAKER_02]: Or, like, when we record these things, it's always like, I keep insisting on being aware of your situation, and then, while you're aware of situation, you look at other things within that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because it's doing exactly the same principle.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, while I am a king,
[SPEAKER_02]: There are all these things that I own, because of which I'm a king, while I am a king right here, right now.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, while I'm king right here, right now, what if I were to lose my castle?
[SPEAKER_02]: I would not be a king anymore, while I'm a king right now.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's how you will also be unable to remain indifferent to your ownership or loss of ownership.
[SPEAKER_02]: The only true way to be indifferent towards it is to abandon any sense of ownership.
[SPEAKER_02]: But if you start looking for ownership and abandoning ownership, like undoing the saṅkharas and whatnot, not through the sense of self, but as an afterthought, as a management technique, as a meditation technique, as a magical hope that it will happen at the end of it, your sense of self remains unaffected, which means you'll be owning that now.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's exactly why people would get upset.
[SPEAKER_02]: And you basically...
[SPEAKER_02]: If somebody, yeah, disagrees, even on the level, like, says your meditation technique is wrong, you get upset.
[SPEAKER_02]: Even if I'm wrong in saying that you are wrong, if you are getting upset, that's a problem... that should be a problem for you.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's a red flag.
[SPEAKER_02]: If you come across someone else's views and you get upset on account of that, that should tell you a lot.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's a work for you to do.
[SPEAKER_02]: Instead, if you truly understood, you will be able to see wrong views as wrong views and right views as right views.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, if somebody comes and says you are wrong, you will be able to see whether they are wrong in saying that,
[SPEAKER_02]: Or, whether they are right in saying that, in which case, you'll be more than happy to upgrade your behavior.
[SPEAKER_02]: But it needs to be taken on that personal level, which is initially unpleasant, and that's why everybody refuses it.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why we just discussed that before, like, how the most rational people would abandon the whole intellect, if something pokes, triggers their feelings.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's unpleasant for me, as a king, to think how I'm a king.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not because I'm a king, but because I have all these things that define me as a king.
[SPEAKER_02]: Now, I can think about those things as an afterthought, when I don't really think through the feeling of being threatened as a king.
[SPEAKER_02]: No, I just think and maybe ponder on the days when I have energy.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's usually how most people practice the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_02]: When I have something particular to deal with, or, like, you know, when I feel like it.
[SPEAKER_02]: But, no.
[SPEAKER_02]: Needs to be done on that... That's why, like, existentially, I'm prey to suffering, as they would have described.
[SPEAKER_02]: Means, you're always on the verge of anxiety, recognizing that, yeah, all this can be uprooted in a finger snap, and you cannot even conceive how to prevent it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, if that's your context, you would be seeing everything else that's kind of going against it, which is any form of ownership, any form of lust, passion, anger, distraction, carelessness.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's against that context.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why it's unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's against that context?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Of things being... yourself being determined?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: You know?
[SPEAKER_02]: You are because you keep taking things to be yours.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's where that right order of things depends.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because you'll be looking at the same thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: It will be a completely wrong thing if you don't see it through the right order.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's when people in the suttas would understand the Buddha first time.
[SPEAKER_02]: You'll be like, wow, it's like putting that which was second, putting it first, and putting first which was second.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's all there.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, there's nothing new can be introduced.
[SPEAKER_02]: But, oh, but I thought,
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it goes on to say that all
[SPEAKER_00]: Sankhāras are dukkha.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: All sankhāras are unownable.
[SPEAKER_02]: All sankhāras are dukkha, because they're unownable.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, because all things, through your sense of self, they determine your sense of self, cannot... you cannot be their master.
[SPEAKER_02]: They are unownable because of that.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can't own them.
[SPEAKER_02]: You took the ownership given to you for granted.
[SPEAKER_02]: But the fact that ownership was given to you means you can't own it, because it can be taken away, like a borrowed gold, borrowed jewelry, they would say.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, because all these saṅkharas, through my sense of self, cannot be owned, that's why they cannot be like a basis for lasting satisfaction, for pleasure.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why they are suffering.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why they are unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because of that, this sense of self is thus up.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not like the conclusion.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, seeing that this sense of self... Yeah, it's a direct recognition.
[SPEAKER_00]: ...determined by these things, thus... That sense of self is then automatically not felt as mine.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, because it's the thing which is not mine.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: All dhammas.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why I keep saying, like, if you see... if you see anicca and dukkha correctly, you don't then have to go and figure out anatta.
[SPEAKER_02]: Seeing anicca and dukkha correctly means seeing anicca and dukkha through your sense of self, which then means seeing anicca and dukkha, this sense of self, through which I'm seeing this, cannot be mine.
[SPEAKER_02]: So your experience as a whole is the experience of anatta.
[SPEAKER_01]: But even seeing impermanence and suffering as being bound up with each other and inseparable, I think a lot of people think... See it out there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, they see that things are kind of... That's why it's not...
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not the Amitabha who talks about it.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why I keep saying it's unownable.
[SPEAKER_02]: In fact, the feeling that the knee is actually just in this state of flux is actually quite pleasant.
[SPEAKER_02]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_02]: Or when people say, look, the modern science has proven everything is impermanent.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's not what impermanence is.
[SPEAKER_02]: Impermanence is un-ownability.
[SPEAKER_02]: Modern science cannot prove that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Which can only be felt as... On the level of ownership or non-ownership, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can say, look, this is impermanent, this is impermanent, this is impermanent, this is impermanent.
[SPEAKER_02]: Everything is impermanent, but it's still, it's not seen as impermanent things that determine me right here, right now.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's just seen in relation to me right here, right now.
[SPEAKER_02]: Thus, I'm saying, I am, and all these things that can be mine are not mine, but I still am, basically.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, in order to see anicca and dukkha correctly,
[SPEAKER_02]: In order to see saṅkhara correctly, it needs to be seen through the sense of self.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, in order to see our own ability correctly, you need to see it through the sense of ownership.
[SPEAKER_02]: And it has to be a threat.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: To the ownership.
[SPEAKER_02]: And it's a threat if it's seen as that ownership depends upon it, not relates to it externally.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it has to be that whole threat to where you're beginning.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: As I said, it's a threat if it's seen that your ownership
[SPEAKER_02]: It depends upon it, not merely relates to it externally.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because usually that's how people observe on each other, like external relationship, and then I infer that thus I am impermanent.
[SPEAKER_02]: But that's it.
[SPEAKER_02]: I am, I don't question that, impermanent.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you just kind of quote another set of belief on top of your unquestioned sense of I am, and implicit ownership of things.
[SPEAKER_02]: And same, you want to see dukkha correctly, you have to see through your sense of... through the pleasurability of your sense of self, of your sense of ownership, of your sense of I am, through the safety of your sense of I am.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's how you see the threat.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not like safety, threat is over there.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's not a threat.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: You want to be... to see that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Actually, to have the knowledge of anatta, you have to go through that anxiety... Existential unravelling.
[SPEAKER_00]: You are going to die.
[SPEAKER_00]: You've got no basis.
[SPEAKER_00]: Your basis is determined.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yourself is determined by things which are not... Again, the suttas talk about it so many times.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you're not going to feel good about it.
[SPEAKER_02]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're going to feel that dukkha.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're going to feel the weight of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: The significance of having to do that.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the other thing, most people feel that something's wrong.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: When you start to see things correctly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: No, that's the whole point.
[SPEAKER_02]: I mean, it's so to say, like, the noble search will come out once you recognize.
[SPEAKER_02]: There are only two outcomes of fully recognizing the nature of suffering correctly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Mindfulness of the party leads to...
[SPEAKER_02]: Mental derangement or search, noble search.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, once you face that existential anxiety, you will either lose your mind, or if you compose well, develop your virtue beforehand,
[SPEAKER_02]: So, if you're developed in terms of your behavior, you won't go mad, but it doesn't mean you won't feel the weight of that anxiety.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's what it says.
[SPEAKER_02]: In other words, you can't remain indifferent.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can't go back to your life you know before.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because you've already undone a great deal of ignorance by becoming aware of anxiety.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why I keep saying anxiety is not a problem, it's a symptom, basically.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's the beginning of recognition of what your existence is.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, it indicates your actual state.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: I was sorry, I was just saying that your mindfulness of the body leads to great existential dread.
[SPEAKER_01]: Who says that?
[SPEAKER_01]: Where says that?
[SPEAKER_01]: That's Anguttarinikaya.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's still those suttas about the mindfulness of the body, the benefits of mindfulness of the body, and the first one is
[SPEAKER_02]: Maybe I do.
[SPEAKER_02]: I don't know.
[SPEAKER_02]: But, no, that's exactly what you're saying.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's a good thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, it's a good thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's a necessary basis.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'm prey to suffering.
[SPEAKER_02]: A young man thinks that, and then, because of that, goes to the holy land, wants to practice, wants to commit his life to the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_02]: As in, not to the lofty serving of the dhamma society, but to actually become an arahant and free himself.
[SPEAKER_02]: Practice it.
[SPEAKER_02]: How would you feel if you were prey?
[SPEAKER_02]: So, yeah, it's unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_02]: What's the first attitude towards this pleasure?
[SPEAKER_02]: I want to get rid of it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, now you know that's not what you should be acting out of.
[SPEAKER_02]: Stop trying to get rid of it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that will then force you to start to learn how to see through it.
[SPEAKER_02]: But, yeah, if you get it and say, oh, no, no, no, no, that's wrong.
[SPEAKER_02]: Don't even go there.
[SPEAKER_02]: Just watch your nostrils.
[SPEAKER_02]: Feel the soles of your feet.
[SPEAKER_02]: Stop thinking.
[SPEAKER_02]: Stop
[SPEAKER_01]: That will free you from your... from the existential suffering and everything else.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why the Buddha and the Satipaṭṭhāna and a number of places talks about the difference between feeling like...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yeah, you've got unpleasant feeling, pleasant feeling, but you've got feeling of the flesh and āmiṣā and feeling that's not of the flesh, nirāmiṣā.
[SPEAKER_01]: So... and that needs... that needs to be distinguished.
[SPEAKER_01]: You need to kind of recognize, okay, this is unpleasant, but it isn't essential.
[SPEAKER_01]: It isn't anything to do with the senses, this unpleasant feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: Zen is essential danger.
[SPEAKER_01]: Danger of essential domain.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.